Guide to the Gary Herbert Howells Papers 1933-2012
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Gary Herbert Howells Papers
1933-2012
Montana State University-Bozeman Library, Merrill G Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2614, MtBC, us
Howells, Gary Herbert 1933-2000
3.3 linear feet
The Gary Herbert Howells Papers consists of correspondence with customers, fellow rod builders, fly tiers, and anglers from across the world.
Biographical Note
Gary Howells was a renowned designer and manufacturer of high-quality bamboo fly rods. He worked for Winston Rod Company until 1970 when he went out on his own as a rod builder. Because of high demand Gary limited rods to one per customer per year. He was also an avid angler who fished across the Western U.S. Canada, and South America. Gary won several Field and Stream awards for fish caught during the early 1960’s. Gary passed away on April 9, 2000 in Richmond, California.
The Gary Herbert Howells Papers consists of correspondence with customers, fellow rod builders, fly tiers, and anglers from across the world. Also included are business records from 1957-1997 that includes receipts, cashed checks, and accounting records. Additional items include fishing diaries detailing angling experiences from 1948-1975, as well as photo albums and personal slides of rivers, insects, fish, rods, family and friends.
This collection is open for research.
Correspondence, business records, diaries, photo albums, and 35 mm slides were purchased by Montana State University Library from Craig Lynch in 2016.
Business and Corporations; Fishing and Canning; Sports and Recreation; Water and Water Rights; Montana; Photographs; Electronic Records
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 1/5-8)
- Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 1/9-12)
- Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 1/13-14)
- Correspondence, 1977 (Box-folder 2/1-4)
- Correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 2/5-8)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 3/1-2)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 3/3-4)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 3/5)
- Correspondence, 1983 (Box-folder 3/6)
- Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 3/7)
- Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 3/8-9)
- Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 3/10)
- Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 3/11)
- Correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 3/12)
- Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 3/13)
- Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 3/14)
- Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 4/1)
- Correspondence, 1992 (Box-folder 4/2)
- Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 4/3)
- Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 4/4)
- Correspondence, 1995 (Box-folder 4/5)
- Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 4/6)
- Correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 4/7)
- Correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 4/8)
- Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 4/9)
- Correspondence, 2000 (Box-folder 4/10)
- Correspondence, 2007 (Box-folder 4/11)
- Correspondence, 2012 (Box-folder 4/12)
- Correspondence, H. Thomas Payne (Box-folder 4/13)
- Correspondence, Craig T. Lynch (Box-folder 4/14)
- Correspondence, Martin J. Keane (Box-folder 4/15)
- Correspondence, Dan Klein (Box-folder 4/16)
- Correspondence, Undated (Box-folder 4/17)
- Field and stream awards, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 4/18)
- Business Records, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 5/1)
- Business Records, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5/2)
- Business Records, 1965 (Box-folder 5/3)
- Business Records, 1968 (Box-folder 5/4)
- Business Records, 1969 (Box-folder 5/5)
- Business Records, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5/6)
- Business Records, 1973 (Box-folder 5/7)
- Business Records, 1974 (Box-folder 5/8)
- Business Records, 1975 (Box-folder 5/9)
- Business Records, 1976 (Box-folder 5/10)
- Business Records, 1977 (Box-folder 5/11)
- Business Records, 1978 (Box-folder 5/12)
- Business Records, 1979 (Box-folder 5/13)
- Business Records, 1980 (Box-folder 5/14)
- Business Records, 1981 (Box-folder 5/15)
- Business Records, 1982 (Box-folder 6/1)
- Business Records, 1983 (Box-folder 6/2)
- Business Records, 1984 (Box-folder 6/3)
- Business Records, 1985 (Box-folder 6/4)
- Business Records, 1986 (Box-folder 6/5)
- Business Records, 1987 (Box-folder 6/6)
- Business Records, 1988 (Box-folder 6/7)
- Business Records, 1989 (Box-folder 6/8)
- Business Records, 1990 (Box-folder 6/9)
- Business Records, 1991 (Box-folder 6/10)
- Business Records, 1992 (Box-folder 6/11)
- Business Records, 1993 (Box-folder 6/12)
- Business Records, 1994 (Box-folder 6/13)
- Business Records, 1995 (Box-folder 6/14)
- Business Records, 1996 (Box-folder 6/15)
- Business Records, 1997 (Box-folder 6/16)
- Notebook: excise tax, 1986-1997 (Box-folder 6/17)
- Family history, certificate, article, and licenses, August 13, 1959; 1948-1955 (Box-folder 7/1)
  Petereit Family History; Copy of Birth Certificate for Gary Herbert Howells; Article titled Ol’ Reverend Lang with rejection letter from Outdoor Life dates August 13, 1959; Fishing license from Idaho, Montana and Wyoming 1948-1955
- Photographs, #1-30 (Box-folder 7/2)
- Photo album 1 (Box-folder 7/3)
- Photo album 2 (Box-folder 7/4)
- Photo album 3 (Box-folder 7/5)
- Fishing diaries, 1948-1950; 1965; 1969; 1970-1974; 1975 (Box-folder 7/6)
- Books 1-3 Slides, 1959-1990 (Box 8)
  Note: USB containing digital surrogates for the fishing, flies, and family slides with a key created by Gregg Messel available.